# Hector Bahamonde, PhD

Instituto de Ciencias Sociales cp (CL): +56-9-4-597-4203
Universidad de O'Higgins cp (US): +1(504) 941-9131
Chile e: hector.bahamonde@uoh.cl
w: www.HectorBahamonde.com

CV last updated: May 27, 2019.

Download latest CV here.

## Bio

Dr. Hector Bahamonde, an Assistant Professor of Political Science, has a successful academic career in Chile. He earned his PhD in the United States, where he also received a post-doctoral fellowship too. Now, being 34 years old, he's trying to relocate to Europe, get a non-academic job, and make use of his methodological training and communication-interpersonal skills outside academia. Married to a German woman, both want to improve their work/life balance, and spend more time with Tobias (2 years-old) and Olimpia (1 year-old).

## Education

## Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey-New Brunswick

Ph.D. Political Science, September 2012–May 2017.

Dissertation: "State Capacities in Latin America: Structural Transformations, Elite Competition, and Fiscal Development (1850-2010)."

Committee: Robert Kaufman (chair), Daniel Kelemen, Douglas Blair, Paul Poast (University of Chicago).

Fields: Comparative Politics and Quantitative Methodology.

#### Catholic University of Chile-Santiago.

B.A. Political Science, 2005–2009.

## **Employment**

#### Universidad de O'Higgins, Rancagua, Chile

Assistant Professor (tenure-track), July 2018-

### Tulane University, New Orleans, LA, United States

Post-Doctoral Fellow, Center for Inter-American Policy & Research (CIPR), June 2017 - June 2018

## Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ, United States

Teaching Assistant, September 2014 - May 2017

Hector Bahamonde, PhD

## Skills

## Certified Methods Proficiency

I have graduate-level statistics training in forecasting, vector auto-regression and error correction models, Bayesian analyses, survey, laboratory and quasi experiments, linear and generalized statistical models, regression discontinuity and diff-in-diff designs. These certifications were obtained at the **University of Michigan** (Ann Arbor), **Princeton** and **Rutgers** University (Statistics Msc programme). Below, I detail some of the courses I've taken:

- "Time Series," "Advanced Time Series."
- "Introduction to Bayesian Analysis."
- "Advanced Ordinary Least Square Methods," "Regression Analysis."
- "Advanced Maximum Likelihood-Estimation" and "Panel Data Analyses."
- "Introduction to Game Theory" and "Formal Modeling."
- "Experimental Methods," "Causal Inference for the Social Sciences."

## Data-Oriented and Computational Social Scientist

Trained as an academic, I have deep understanding and experience in applied social research. In particular, I'm passionate about working with big datasets, causal inference (lab/survey experiments), quasi-experiments (matching for observational studies) and programming (R and Stata). You can check my coding expertise in my GitHub. Teaching and presenting at conferences are my daily routine; I'm passionate about communicating results effectively.

#### *Interpersonal*

I have considerable experience as an independent critical person, used to work under pressure, and goal-oriented. Not only do I have good writing/analytical skills, but also excellent interpersonal relationships. Having both excellent leadership skills and willingness to collaborate with others, make me an ideal candidate to take different roles, for instance in different projects, in the same institution.

## **Others**

Languages: English, Spanish.

Advanced Software Usage: R, Stata, LATEX.

#### Research

Please note, every paper employs different sophisticated—still applied—econometric techniques.

#### Peer-Reviewed Articles

- Bahamonde, H. (2018). Aiming Right at You: Group versus Individual Clientelistic Targeting in Brazil. *Journal of Politics in Latin America*, 10(2), pp. 41-76.
- Bahamonde, H. (2011). El Secreto de mi Éxito: Parte II. Los Caminos a Valparaíso en 2009. Revista de Ciencia Política, 31(2), pp. 285-310. With Pilar Giannini, Juan Pablo Luna, Rodolfo López, Martín Ordoñez and Gonzalo Recart.

Hector Bahamonde, PhD 3

## Work in Progress

• Income Taxation and State Capacity in Chile: Measuring Institutional Development Using Historical Earthquake Data, *under review, Comparative Politics*. Lead paper.

- Still for Sale: The Micro-Dynamics of Vote-Selling in the United States, Evidence From a List and Conjoint Experiments, *under review*, Electoral Studies.
- Sectoral Origins of Income Taxation: Industrial Development in Latin America, and The Case of Chile (1900-2010), *in preparation*.
- Structural Transformations and State Institutions in Latin America, 1900-2010, in preparation.
- Testing the Online Model of Candidate Evaluation in a More Realistic Environment, *in preparation*. With Richard Lau (Rutgers) and Mona Kleinberg (UMass Lowell).
- Inclusive Institutions, Unequal Outcomes: Democracy, State Infrastructural Power, and Inequality 1970-2015, *submitted*. With Mart Trasberg (Tulane).

#### Book Reviews in Peer-Reviewed Journals (Invited)

• Inés Durán Matute. "Indigenous Peoples and the Geographies of Power: Mezcala's Narratives of Neoliberal Governance" (Routledge). *Journal of Iberian and Latin American Research*.

## **Chapters**

• ¿Estable Pero Sin Raíces? Los Partidos Políticos Chilenos en la Opinión Pública, in *Cultura Política de la Democracia en Chile, Ch. IX, LAPOP Country Report, 2010.* With Juan Pablo Luna, Germán Bidegain, Roody Reserve and Giancarlo Visconti.

## Career Objective

I want to help institutions (big or small) to reach their goals by incorporating my academic experience. By bringing my analytical skills, and excellent interpersonal relationships, I am interested in both leading teams and collaborating with others. My ideal institution lets its employees be innovative, goal-oriented and creative. I have immediate availability, and I'm ready to relocate tomorrow.